<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iacob is become a flame and the house of Esav stubble, or, The battail betwixt Michael and the dragon in which the seed of the woman is bruising the serpents head, and Cain the first birth ... is found the vagabond, and Abel and Abraham ... the friends of God : being a true discovery of the two seeds or births between which the enmity is put, the time and day being come in which the elder must serve the younger : with a few words to the priests, Bishops, Episcopal-men, and professors of this last age, and a short warning to the rulars and inhabitants of the earth.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27128</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09658004</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09658004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27130)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1324:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iacob is become a flame and the house of Esav stubble, or, The battail betwixt Michael and the dragon in which the seed of the woman is bruising the serpents head, and Cain the first birth ... is found the vagabond, and Abel and Abraham ... the friends of God : being a true discovery of the two seeds or births between which the enmity is put, the time and day being come in which the elder must serve the younger : with a few words to the priests, Bishops, Episcopal-men, and professors of this last age, and a short warning to the rulars and inhabitants of the earth.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: W.B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Wrath.</term>
               <term>Judgment of God.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43937:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IACOB is become a FLAME and the houſe of ESAV Stubble.</p>
            <p>Or the Battail betwixt <hi>Michael</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> in which the Seed of the woman is bruiſing the <hi>Serpents Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Cain</hi> the firſt Birth <hi>(the Perſecutor)</hi> is found the Vagabond and <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> (that wandred) the freinds of God.</p>
            <p>Being a true diſcovery of the two ſeeds or births, between which the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is put, the time and day being come in which the Elder muſt ſerve the Younger.</p>
            <p>With a few words to the Prieſts, Biſhops, Epiſcopal-men, and profeſſors of this laſt Age, and a ſhort warning to the Rulars and Inhabitants of the EARTH.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>Do men gather Grapes of Thorns or Figs of Thiſtles.</head>
            <p>IN the beginning God created the Heavens and the Earth, the Sea and all living Creatures, and the end of their creation was to ſerve, and manifeſt the glory &amp; wiſdome, power &amp; goodneſs of God their Creator, and for no other end were they Created in the beginning, and that all his works of Creation ſhould be in ſubjection unto him, being ruled and governed by his pure Righteous power, Counſel, and wiſdome.</p>
            <p>And to the end that his wonders, and power, and goodneſs, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might be the more manifeſt, he endued man with a proportion of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43937:2"/> the ſame, that he himſelf is, even pure, wiſdome, Love, Holineſs, Truth, Juſtice and Goodneſs, or whatſoever might be named of the properties and qualities of the Creator, (mark) this was the end of Gods Creation, (eſpecially of mankind) to ſet forth his own glorious virtues, and holy righteous power, that ſo his workmanſhip might be a continual praiſe unto him, living in ſubjection to that pure power, by which they were created; this was Gods end even to glorifie himſelf in theſe things.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſaid his dear Son (who came to reſtore man, and the whole Creation into its firſt ſtate) <hi>Herein is my Father glorified that you manifeſt or bring forth good fruits,</hi> (mark) this glorifies God, and his end of Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by this is anſwered even the bringing forth of thoſe virtues in power and life again: But whileſt man is in the tranſgreſſion, ſeperation and alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from God, he anſwers not the end of his Creation, but is out of his right and proper habitation fallen ſhort of his glory; neither can he mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Gods wonders, and power, wiſdome and truth, and goodneſs in that ſtate, but doth manifeſt and bring forth the power and lying wonders, works and properties of the wicked one, which is called the old Serpent the Divel and Satan, whoſe workings are contrary to God, and the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of his Creation, therefore is he called the Adverſary and was known ſo to be, by the true Seed in all Ages, who came again to be reſtored into that ſtate in which they enjoyed the power and virtues and wiſdome of God, and ſo in the end of their Creation, even bearing good fruits, glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying God in body, ſoul and ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Now conſider, man in the beginning was made uprightly, and planted a noble Vine, and in that ſtate was bleſſed of God his Creator, in whoſe power and virtues he ſhould have continued, and in the wiſdome autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and dominion thereof to have ruled over all the Creation, yet as a ſubject to that power by which he was made and created, and not aſpire above it (mark that) for it was ſo, and this was the firſt appearance of the Adverſary, even to draw out the ſimple mind to be more wiſe, knowing and ſeeking ſomething to himſelf, with a promiſe (mark that) ye ſhall be as Gods, knowing, to which hearkning, and obeying, the upright and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mind is deceived and beguiled of that wiſdome, Power, Glory, and Bleſſedneſs which endures for ever, and ſo feeds on that which dyes of it ſelf, againſt the command of God, for knowledge doth vaniſh away, but the life, power, and bleſſings of God endures for ever, and will never dye, though Heaven and Earth may paſs away.</p>
            <p>Therefore conſider O mankind, in what ſtate thou wert at firſt created, and by what ſpirit and power thou waſt then upheld and guided, and to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43937:2"/> what ſtate or ſeed, the everlaſting bleſſings of God the Creator, are due and of right unto; for now are the Springs and Fountains of the great deep broke open unto the children of men, and the great day of God and the Lamb is manifeſt and come, in which all things, works and fruits ſhall be proved and tryed of what ſeed, root, or ground ſoever, and every ſeed ſhall have his own body <hi>(he that hath an ear to hear let him hear)</hi> and now ſhall the ſeed and body of the Serpent, call to the Mountains and Rocks to fall on them, to hide them from the wrath of the Lamb (the womans ſeed) and of him that ſits upon the throne, to whom be bleſſings and goodneſs, all glory and honour Amen, for ever.</p>
            <p>Now this was the Serpents ſeed, (whoſe head is and muſt be bruiſed) that at its beginning ſprang up in the mind, with a deceivable promiſe of being wiſe, and knowing of himſelf, lifting up above, and without reſpect of ſubjection to his Creator, ſo from this root grew pride, ſelfiſhneſs, earthly wiſdome, and diſobedience to every good motion of that holy righteous power, by which he was created, and here is that Proverb true <hi>After pride comes a fall,</hi> for its not of God, but abomination to him, and the ſeed of evil doers ſhall never be renowned, but muſt be bruiſed by the dread and power of the Lord of Heaven and earth, and be chained down as a ſlave of abominations for ever; and the day is come in which the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath laid hold on this Dragon, and will ſeal him down into the pit of perdition no more to ariſe and deceive the Nations of the Earth, and the Ax of his diſpleaſure (againſt unrighteouſneſs) is laid at the root of the great tree of wickedneſs, and down muſt it come as a Milſtone that is caſt into the depth of the Sea, as you have heard of <hi>Babylon,</hi> for this is the Mother (or original) of all Harlots and abominations of the earth, and they that live in wickedneſs, and take pleaſure in ungodlineſs, are the children of this womb of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> where all is out of the true order, and ſubjection of the Holy pure God of truth, yet are wiſe to do evil, but to do good have no knowledge, being lifted up out of the fear of God that made them: yet there is a government, and kingdome, and fruits and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of this ſeed of wickedneſs, in the time of its reign and predominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. As there is of the ſeed of God in its reign and government, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in nature, fruits and effects, and this wicked deceivable one hath got a Church, Religious, Worſhips, and Orders, (as they call them) and are in the imitation of the true ſeed things (like <hi>Cain</hi>) but from the root of confuſion and enmity as by its fruits and effects is manifeſt through the Creation of God: this is that <hi>Elder</hi> which muſt [now] ſerve the <hi>Younger,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43937:3"/> having had its day; (or rather night) and time to manifeſt it ſelf fully in the Creation, that ſo the juſt God might Judge, and deſtroy it, Root, and branch, with a witneſs; and that every mouth may be ſtopt and ſilent, but what ſhall juſtifie the Righteous Judge in his Judgments which are equal, juſt, and true.</p>
            <p>And this time of the growth, manifeſtation, Reigne, and Government of this Seed (the man of Sin, or ſon of perdition, which hath been exalted above all that is called God;) And the ſufferings and oppreſſions of the Righteous ſeed, hath been the time of the Creators forbearance, long ſuffering, and patience, (he that can hear, let him hear) even the long ſuffering of the Lord God gratious and merciful, whoſe <hi>Name is I AM</hi> and beſides him there is no <hi>Saviour,</hi> (he that can receive it let him) and happy is the man that hath him on his ſide, and that he may not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for the great God is come, to move and to remove, and ſhake all foundations, Roots, Seeds, Plants, and Trees that are not of the Root of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> the <hi>Plant</hi> of his own Right hand's planting; And wickedneſs ſhall be broaken as a tree: Therefore look to it you ungodly ones, (ye ſeed of evil doers, (for your time is ſhort, you have had your day, (or rather your hour and power of darkneſs) in which you have delighted to live in, and manifeſt the Root and fruits of the wicked one, even the Serpents ſeed, which hath been bruiſing the heel of the womans ſeed, even cauſing them to ſuffer by reproaches, cruel mockings, and perſecutions, as your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <hi>Iſhmael, Cain,</hi> and <hi>Haman,</hi> with many more of the ſame ſeed and ſtock, have done to the Righteous ſeed in Ages paſt, but now are the laſt of that Generation, even the <hi>Dragons Tayle;</hi> which think to draw down the ſtars of Heaven by your power of pride, Rage and madneſs, and are caſting out many flouds of Venome againſt the woman, and the remnant of her ſeed, which keeps the Commandments and teſtimony of Jeſus: But it's in vaine for you to ſtrive againſt God the Creator of heaven and earth, woe is your portion (in ſo doing) you will be ground to powder in the dreadful day at hand.</p>
            <p>For as I have received of the mighty God in his eternal Counſel, do I declare unto you, that you that now are in the Spirit of Pride, Envy, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, uncleaneſs, Pleaſures of this evil world, Scoffing and deriding the poor and harmleſs, and are in the flattering titles, and reſpecting perſons, and forcing, and perſecuting about Religion and Worſhip, in diſdainful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, fullneſs and Idleneſs, Hypocricy and all manner of unrighteouſneſs, I ſay you that are in this ſeed or ſpirit, which brings forth theſe fruits and effects, whether you be Popes, Emperours, Biſhops, Kings, Prieſts, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43937:3"/> Dukes, Earles, or Counſels of ungodly men, or any other of theſe flattering titles you bear, you are of the ſame ſeed, ſtock, or offspring, as was <hi>Cain, Iſhmael, Haman, Eſau,</hi> and the reſt of that Generation, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the Scriptures of truth out of whoſe Loynes proceeded many Princes, as were the Princes of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and Dukes of <hi>Edom,</hi> which were of <hi>Eſaus</hi> ſtock, who ſould his Birth-right for a meſſe of Pottage: Hear this ye ungodly, and ſet your ears tingle, for this is your ſtate who for the ſatisfiing the Luſts of the fleſhly Birth (which are but for a ſeaſon) that war againſt your ſouls, have loſt the comfort, reſt, and eternal peace thereof, in the ſalvation of the pure Righteous God; and inſtead of fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his great and dread full Name, and departing from iniquity, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting to the ſtrivings, and reprofes of his Light and holy Spirit, (which lets you ſee the evil of your ways) you are like <hi>Goliah</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed Philiſtine, who defied the Armies of the living God, and are vaunting your ſelves with your Challenges, upbraiding, and deridings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for whoſe ſake he will break the ſtrength of Nations, as he did in the days paſt when they were oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>And be it known to you, who are in the ſeed and ſpirit before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by what names or flattering titles ſoever you are called, oppreſſing the innocent, (who have no helper in the earth, but the living God alone) and are living in the pleaſures of ſin, and ways of unrighteouſneſs; you are unto God the pure eternal Jehovah of Iſrael, even as <hi>Pharoah, Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> who are ſmitten with blindneſs, not ſeeing the heavy plagues and dreadful Judgements that are ſwiftly coming upon you: O ye Sons of tranſgreſſion, and children of falſehood, who love the glory and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this world which paſſeth away, and the honour below, and vanity of vanitys, which vexeth the pure ſpirit of the Righteous God, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth your own ſouls; your day haſtens, in which you will be as Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the firery Oven even all you heathen that are at eaſe, for the great and dreadful God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is very ſorely diſpleaſed with you, and the wo and vengeance of his fury burns againſt you, even this laſt Generation of <hi>Perſecutors;</hi> though you may plot, conſult, and decree againſt his rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant whom he hath Redeemed from that ſeed, fruits, works, and ways which you are in, even out of <hi>Babylon</hi> and are brought to <hi>Sion,</hi> where they declare the vengeance of the Almighty God, againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> the great Whore, (whored from God the contrary to God) which hath ruled, and ſat over Nations; I ſay though you may combine and contrive much, in the abundance of the wicked counſels of your hearts, and decree unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous decrees, yet you ſhall not proſper nor prevaile to accompliſh your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43937:4"/> intents, and purpoſes againſt my people, (I the Lord have ſpoken it) no more then <hi>Pharoah, Goliah, Herod,</hi> or <hi>Haman</hi> did, who ſought the young Childs life to deſtroy it, but was prevented, ſo you may conſider it did ever any fight againſt God, his ſeed and people, and proſper; But you may object being of the contrary ſeed, and ſay, are you the ſeed of God, or his people, againſt whom we have made Laws and decrees, traps, and ſnares, even you that are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> for we look upon you as Hereticks, diſobedient and dangerous perſons, not ſubmiting to Governments, not honouring Authority, nor reſpecting perſons, nor giving us (flattering) titles, but are of another generation, then we are of, therefore do we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and contrive how to deſtroy you, from being a people by impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpoyling of goods, and baniſhment, and death alſo if we could bring it about, and that even the whole Nation would not riſe againſt it, for all ſober people (we perceive) are affected with you and your ways and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings amongſt them, by which we are afraid to proceed ſo far, as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is in our hearts to do. To which I ſhall anſwer in the Name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>That we who by the ſinful and adulterous generation, are ſcornfully called <hi>Quakers,</hi> are the people, ſervants, and children of the moſt high God, which might be demonſtrated, or proved, paralel to his choſen ſeed and people in all Ages, by the ſpirit, ways, worſhip, and practiſes, life, and converſation of his ſervants and Children from the beginning to this day.</p>
            <p>Firſt conſider there are but two ſeeds in the whole Creation, between which emnity is put, and are obſolute contrary in Nature, fruits, and effects, that is the ſeed of the Serpent; And the ſeed of the <hi>Woman,</hi> which is Chriſt (in his people) the ſame to day, yeſterday and for ever the <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> who is now coming in ten thouſands of thouſands of his Saints cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers</hi> who tremble at his word, for they are the people that ſhall ſpring up and ſpread from the Root of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> over the face of the whole Earth, through the vertue and power of this ſeed Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe fruits and effects, is <hi>Love,</hi> meekneſs, patience, temperance, mercy, fulneſs, juſtneſs, ſoberneſs, righteouſneſs, holineſs, peace, and joy in the eternal power and ſpirit of the pure God, doing to all men as they would they ſhould do to them: theſe and ſuch like are the fruits of the tree of this ſeed of the Woman, (Chriſt) which muſt bruiſe the head of the Serpent, whoſe ſeed brings forth contrary fruits and effects in every particular, though in ſome things it might imitate the Righteous ſeed (as <hi>Cain</hi> did) in matter of ſacrifice, or worſhip, or the like, but ſtill its from another ſeed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43937:4"/> root and ground which is acurſed, for ſaid God curſed is the ground for thy ſake (mark that) the ground not the ſimple earth which is good, but the ground of envy, murder, and wickedneſs, that had opened his mouth (in him) to ſwallow up his brothers blood, from which it cryes againſt him, and his generation of murderers about ſacrifice and worſhip, at this day and for ever, ſo this is the other ſeed, whoſe fruits and effects are manifeſt, as ſaith the Scriptures, (even the ſeed of the fleſhly Birth, which perſecutes the birth born of the Spirit of the living God) which are theſe envy, pride, wrath, malice, ſtriffe, anger, highmindedneſs, frowardneſs, bitterneſs, uncleaneſs, laciviouſneſs, covetouſneſs, drunkeneſs, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toneſs, revellings, rioting, emulations, witchcraft, hatred, hereſies, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, injuſtice partiallity, and hipocriſy, theſe and ſuch like are the fruits and effects of the Serpents ſeed which hath ſpread as a great tree of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs over the whole earth, and is that curſed one that hath ſo long cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the ground.</p>
            <p>And theſe are alſo the Children of <hi>Babylon</hi> the great Whore which hath Reigned over the Nations, and Kings of the Earth, happy is the man that daſheth theſe againſt the ſtone, (Chriſt Jeſus the light that diſcovers them) and theſe are thoſe wares &amp; coſtlineſs, &amp; pretious things of <hi>Babylon,</hi> even the fruits and pleaſures of ſin, the glory, riches, worſhips, and belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed practiſes of iniquity, which proceeds from this ſeed of falſehood, ſatisfying a ground that is accurſed for ever; Therefore ſaith God come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> my people pertake not of her ſins (or fruits) that ye be not pertakers of her plagues.</p>
            <p>And now is the day come, in which <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall receive at the hand of the Almighty, the Cup of the wine of his fury and indignation without mixture, and ſhall drink the dregs thereof and wring them out, and all her Marchants that have lived deliciouſly, and delighted in her wares and coſtlineſs, and traded with her, ſhall houl, wail and lament, beholding the ſmoak of her torments which aſcends up for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>Hear this, you ſuperſtitious, and Idolatrous Prieſts, Biſhops and Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, for the fooliſh woman, whoſe feet are not in her houſe, but is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, loud, ſtubborn, and clamourous, is now pulling down her own houſe with her hands <hi>(mark that)</hi> by her own ungodly actions, wicked words and practiſes, ſlanders, perſecutions, and greivous abominations even pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or drawing down the juſt judgements, plagues, and eternal venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the righteous God upon her own head, (he that reads let him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand) for the time is at hand) therefore conſider, all ye that live in enmity againſt the harmleſs ſeed and people this day, are not you in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43937:5"/> pride which is abomination to God, and Ambition and Covetouſneſs, which is Idolatry, and love pleaſures and vanities, luſts of uncleanneſs, deceit and flattery, more then the pure living God of truth and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and are not you in the ſtoutheartedneſs, diſdainfulneſs, feignedneſs and Hypocriſy, diſſimulation and all manner of wickedneſs, and are not you become the hold of every foul ſpirit, and cage of unclean and hateful birds, read your ſtate, and do not ſtrive againſt that, that lets you ſee it, nor ſay no by any pretence or covering; for the dreadful God hath found you out, and his judgements and vengeance is your portion, and the great day of the Lamb is come, in which you are not able to ſtand.</p>
            <p>(This is the ground of your rage, ſeeing you have but a ſhort time) as it is written the wicked cannot ſtand in the judgement, nor ſinners in the Congregation of the Righteous. Therefore hearken all ye who are in the Babiloniſh Garments (the night attire of the great Whore) the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, ſtrong, and powerful God of Heaven and Earth, is ſtripping and making her bare, and naked, as in the day in which ſhe was borne to the the view of all Nations, Men and Angels, for the hour of her judgements is come, her ſins have reached to heaven, and are come into the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance before God, even her envy and rage, ſcorning and diſdaining per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting and cruelty, luſts and pleaſures, and vanities, and all manner of Injuſtice, iniquity and ungodlineſs, flattering and deceitful titles, ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, diſſimulation, Hypocriſy and Idolatry, and the like abominations: this is alſo the tongue of the Egyptian Sea which God Almighty of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, will ſhortly dry up that people may goe over dry-ſhod <hi>(he that hath an ear let him hear and underſtand)</hi> the day haſtens yea, it cometh ſwiftly, in which righteous, juſt, ſober, and godly men and people ſhall walk with boldneſs with comfort and courage in the waies of holineſs, uprightneſs and truth in all the Nations of the earth or elſe the Lord God, hath never ſpoken by me (which I know he hath and will perform it.)</p>
            <p>Therefore tremble ye careleſs daughters that are at eaſe, walking haughtily with ſtretched forth necks and wanton eyes, howl, howl and weep bitterly, ye light puft up and vainglorious men and women, the day of your calamity cometh on like an armed man, and you ſhall not eſcape, and upon all you that cry out againſt the children and ſervants of the moſt high God, ſaying they will not obey Magiſtrates, nor reverence ſuch as are in Authority, nor reſpect and honour Superiors, nor be ſubject to the Kings Laws, but are proud and wilful ſtubborn and diſobedient, and will not worſhip as we worſhip, nor admire mens perſons, though they might have advantage by it.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43937:5"/>
            <p>Hear now my anſwer ye people whoſe portion is in this life, who are of the houſhould and ſtock of <hi>Eſau</hi> the prophane perſon, whoſe houſe is now as Stubble.</p>
            <p>The God of heaven by his dreadful, and Almighty power and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, hath broken in upon us, and laid low the haughtineſs, and hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down the tree of wickedneſs and unrighteouſneſs in us, from whence theſe evil fruits before mentioned, proceeded, and hath redeemed us from our vain converſation in which we were as other Gentiles, walking in the vanitys of our minds, in the Luſts of Ignorance, and hath raiſed up by the ſame power, a ſeed of his own begetting in us, having caſt out the heathen (in us) that knew not God, and prepared roome for his own Life, and power and wiſdome, (which is fooliſhneſs to the world) to take poſſeſſion of our hearts and conſciences for ever, to which our ſouls are ſubject, knowing him to be the higher power, who hath put down all Rule and all Authority (in us) which was contrary to him, who is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our King, and our Law-giver, Teacher and Saviour, which no man can remove from us into a corner, and we are led and guided by his ſpirit, who is the wonderful Counſellour, the mighty God, the Prince of peace, and are not Rebellious, wilful, or ſtubborn neither to God nor man, in what is manifeſt to be his will concerning us.</p>
            <p>And as for Magiſtrates, and ſuch as are in the Authority and power of God, as was <hi>Moſes</hi> and ſuch men fearing God hating covetouſneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and unrighteouſneſs, we dearly own, and honour in the Lord, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſuch as are puniſhers of evil doers, favourers, and encouragers of them that do well, theſe are [Magiſtrats] (in Gods behalfe) bearing the Sword of Juſtice and true Judgement, and not in vain, being (in the power and wiſdome of God) a terrour to evil doers, and a praiſe to them that do well, theſe are worthy of honour, theſe rule well, theſe anſwer the witneſs of God in all people, theſe Judge Righteouſly, equally, and juſtly, without partiallity, in the fear and dread, and domion of God hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſpect to him, and his honour only in what they do, not ſeeking their own honour, (which would periſh) but in meekneſs, ſoberneſs, and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of minde and Judgement, without reſpect of perſons, judging be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and man, being able to diſcerne the ground of all cauſes and controverſies in the Light and Counſel of God, (whoſe ſervants they are) mark that, theſe are [Magiſtrats] &amp; not every one that beareth that name, no more then all that profeſs Chriſt in words, are Chriſtians, who can ſay Lord, Lord, and we are Chriſtians, and we love God, when they hate the light, his own witneſs in them, and walk in darkneſs, being Lyers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43937:6"/> and Hypocrits, for none are Chriſtians, really and in Gods ſight, but they that follow Chriſt in the Regeneration, being borne again through the ſtrength and power, and vertue of his own life and ſpirit, being guided by it, out of all unrighteouſneſs into holineſs, righteouſneſs, and truth, for they that ſay they are Chriſtians and are not are Lyers, and of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoge of Satan, whoſe will and works they do, even they it is that bear the name of [Magiſtrates] and are not really ſo: Now [Magiſtrates] are not a terrour to good works, but to the evil, (mark that) but ſuch as have been, and yet are ſo called, in <hi>England</hi> (New and Old,) have been and yet are a terrour to good works, contrary to the end and will of God, government on Earth, and the very word [Magiſtrate] ſo that ſuch are but like them that ſaid they were Jews and were not, but of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue and generation of him who hath been a lyer from the beginning, for this I teſtifie in the Lord without reſpect of perſons, that ſuch are not [Magiſtrates] ordained by him, that are out of his fear and thoſe good properties, and qualities before mentioned (though they may be rich, and great men in the earth, as <hi>Cain, Eſau,</hi> and <hi>Haman</hi> were, yet are like the Preiſts that bear rule by their means, and not by the power, wiſdome, and mercy of God,) who will rage, and fume, and ſtorme, like a wild Bull in a net, before they have heard the cauſes, and controverſies of ſuch as are brought before them, becauſe the ſpirit of Pride, and Ambition, (which is of the Devil,) is not bowed unto, and will impriſon people (right or wrong) without breach of any [juſt] Law of God or man, theſe are not [Magiſtrates] but evil doers; and [Magiſtrates] are for the puniſhing of evil doers, neither is that a juſt Law (but an unrighteous decree) which is made to be a terrour to good works, and an encouragement to evil doers, this is turning Judgment into Gall, and Righteouſneſs into Hemlock, and the Sword backwards: Conſider theſe things, for with them God is not pleaſed, who beholds the prey that is made on them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity in the Land.</p>
            <p>For ſuch do well (and are not evil doers) who meet together in the fear of the true God, to wait upon him in the light of his counſel, by it to be guided into all truth through the knowledge of his will concerning them and their ſalvation, that ſo they may ſerve God in his holy way ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably all the daies of their life with reverence and godly fear, (for our God is a conſuming fire) and he or ſhe that bears witneſs in the ſpirit of truth, and power of righteouſneſs, againſt Pride, Idolaty, Popery, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, or any other ungodly luſts, deceit or hypocricy, as preaching for money, or Judging for rewards, and ſuch like, Injuſtice, Oppreſſion, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43937:6"/> cruelty, or any of the fruits of the corrupt tree, (which God is hewing down for the fire, I ſay that man or woman, boy or girle, of the ſtreets of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that ſo doth as afore mentioned, in the name of the Lord, doth well; and they that abuſe them for ſo doing, doth evil, and God ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it at their hands, for he or ſhe that ſtands a witneſs in the power, and wiſdome of God (which is the higher power) againſt the fleſhly luſts, which warr againſt the ſoul, is in ſo doing the ſouls freind, (he that can hear let him him hear,) for to the higher power (which was before the luſts and wills of men, or the powers of darkneſs, Death, Hell, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, (the <hi>lower condemned power</hi> was) are we ſubject, and this ſeed (or life) which God hath raiſed in us, (who at this day are called <hi>Quakers</hi>) cannot bow down to the Devil (the lower power) nor worſhip that ſpirit of Pride, enmity, ambition, and wickedneſs, which God hath determined to deſtroy root and branch, and them that live in, and worſhip it, for it is the Image of the old Serpent, the Devil, and deſtroyer of mankind, to which the pure Image or ſon of the living God, could never bow, but was always a ſufferer (for a ſeaſon) under its enmity and cruelty, as may be ſeen throughout all ages to this day, for it is no new thing to ſee him that is born after the fleſh, oppreſs, and perſecute him that is born after the ſpirit; for it began at <hi>Abel,</hi> [even about ſacrifice] and is the ſame at this day, for whatſoever you may ſay, and profeſs in words (<hi>Cain</hi> could alſo talk and contend in the ſame nature) that matters not while you are in the ſpirit of Pride and enmity (which is of the Devil,) your Sacrifice is not accepted, of the Righteous holy God, but is unto him, as an odious ſmoak of Brimſtone in the Noſtrills of a man, and your Church (ſo called) is not the body of Chriſt Jeſus, (the Lambs wife,) but of the great whore, which hath drank the blood of the Saints; living in pleaſures, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, pride, ſcornfulneſs, diſdain, flattery, deceit, and vanity, with your tongues at Liberty out of Gods fear, in wrath and envy, luſt and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs, ſwearing, curſing, and corrupt communication, rioting and ſporting, and all manner of ungodlineſs; theſe are not the fruits of Gods ſpirit (in which he is only worſhiped,) nor graces of Chriſts Church, (but the Whores night garments) for the Chriſtians were, (and are) to abſtain from all appearance of evil, and to waite upon God, through his power to be ſanctified throughout, in body, ſoul, and ſpirit, hating even the garment ſpotted with the fleſh; againſt which work the Serpent and his ſeed, in all Ages have ſet themſelves, and took counſel together, and made Laws and decrees, even to hinder the appearance, growth, and Dominion of the Righteous ſeed, and Image of God which is Chriſt (in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43937:7"/> his people in all generations,) the ſeed of the woman which is bruſing the Serpents head.</p>
            <p>Therefore All ye Rulers, Prieſts, Biſhops, Lip-profeſſors, and people who are gainſayers of the light, the truth, the way of God in his people, and are perſecutors, oppoſers, proud, wanton, diſdainful, wild, ſcornful and rebellious againſt Gods witneſs, that lets you ſee your evil deeds and vain converſation: and all you ſwearers and drunkards, lyers, envious, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleiving whoremongers, hypocrites, whores, ſorcerers, fearful and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, you are all without (without are dogs (the biters) and every one that loveth and maketh a Lye.</p>
            <p>Hear this you that oppoſe the power of the pure dreadful God, and its mighty works amongſt the children of men, which he hath begun in his people, (called Quakers) it is too weighty for you, it ſhall break you to peices, and confound you, (its Gods work you oppoſe and not mans) and if you ſay in your hearts, you will make us bow before you have done with us, I tell you nay, God hath raiſed a ſeed in us of his own life and Image, (can ye not underſtand) which can never bow to unrighteouſneſs, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, hypocricy, and deceit, but ſtand in the Royal power, and Authority of the Living God, bearing teſtimony againſt it, and fear not him that can but kill the body, and after that hath power to do no more, but is in the pure fear, dread, and terrible power of the Almighty God, who hath raiſed it up, compaſſing it about, as a wall of fire and you can never quench it, for it is that love (which is ſtronger then death,) that is ſhed abroad in our hearts, (bleſſed is the man that heareth, beleiveth, and receiveth it,) therefore it is impoſible for you to prevaile againſt it, unleſs you could prevaile againſt God, or were ſtronger then him, then might you hinder his handy works and mighty wonders which he hath determined to bring to paſs in theſe laſt days, for let me tell you the Kings, &amp; Rulers, Prieſts, &amp; Biſhops for to you now am I ſpeaking, and that from the eternal God of Heaven, that you are at this day verily oppoſing the great &amp; weighty work of God which he will accompliſh, &amp; none ſhall be able to hinder, &amp; veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you ſhall as eaſily pluck the Sun, Moon, and Stars, out of the Firmament (in which the living God hath ſet them by his power, and orders them by his wiſdome,) as ſtop, hinder, or fuſtrate the decree or purpoſe of God, concerning his people, and their Enemies in theſe laſt days.</p>
            <p>For the day is come, of which his former Prophets have propheſied, and declared, that in the laſt days, he would poure out of his ſpirit upon his ſons and daughters, and they ſhould prophecy; But this is a ſtrange work which you cannot underſtand, as it is witten, many ſhall be tryed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43937:7"/> purified, and made white, but the wicked, will do wickedly, and none of the wicked ſhall underſtand, but the wiſe ſhall underſtand [who are in that wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which the fear of the Lord is the beginning of:] And in the day when the proud were called happy, &amp; them that tempted God, were even delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, did ſome fear the Lord, and met often together, and thought upon his name, for when a book of remembrance was written before the Lord, and they ſhall be mine ſaith God, &amp; I will ſpare them, as a man ſpareth his ſon that ſerveth him (though men will not ſpare them, who are ſervants of the Devil,) and is not this the day, ye this is the day, even the notable day, the great and dreadful day, in which the mighty God will cut ſhort his work in Righteouſneſs, and becauſe of this, Nations ſhall be diſtreſſed, and in great perplexity, the Sea ſhall roar, and mens hearts ſhall faile them for fear, and for looking after thoſe things which are coming upon the Earth, and men ſhall walk like blind men, becauſe of their Rebellion againſt God, and God ſhall ſend his Plagues upon the Earth, like ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Hail, even Sword, and Famine, and Peſtilence, and Earthquakes, and dreadful Thunderings upon the head of the wicked, and all fleſh ſhall faile before him, and the Mountains ſhall quake at his preſence, for the terible God ſhall roar out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and utter his voice in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the earth ſhall tremble, and pain ſhall take hold of the ungodly as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in travail, and they ſhall not eſcape.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſeek not to get eaſe, and covering, by your unrighteous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees againſt the Saints of the moſt high God, or by afflicting and abuſing them; for we whom you have thus dealt with, are his choſen Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his Royal preiſthood, his peculiar people, zealous of good works, whoſe cauſe he will plead with all fleſh, and there is not a man upon the face of the whole earth, that God hath reſpect unto, or his offering, but in this ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> (which is Chriſt in us) which he hath raiſed to offer up living ſacrifices, acceptable in his ſight, for the ſacrifice of the wicked is abomination to him, and there are but two ſeeds, roots, or grounds (as (I have ſaid) from whence all good and evil ſprings, the one is the ſeed of Gods own ſowing, which is now ariſing to ſpread over the whole earth even the Plant of <hi>Righteouſneſs, Truth,</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> and the other is the ſeed of Enmity againſt God, his truth and people; and this is the ſeed of evil doers, which ſhall never be renowned: And the ſon of God is come the ſeed of Renown, and hath given us an underſtanding, that we know him that is true, (and are in him that is true) and we know him that is falſe and out of the truth, and we know God only is to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Devil denyed, though he might rage, ſtorme, and perſecute,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43937:8"/> or promiſe all the Glory, Kingdoms, and pleaſures of this world, to be bowed unto, or worſhiped, yet the Royal ſeed cannot give glory to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, therefore would the Devil (like his ſon <hi>Haman</hi>) have him deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the world, in which he himſelf hath been worſhiped as God, blinding, and vailing the minde of mankind, from the true knowledge and underſtanding, of the noble ſeed, (the heir) whoſe right it is alone to Reigne, and he muſt Reigne [now] till all his enemies are trampled under his feet, the Lord hath ſpoken it, to whom be all Honour, Worſhip, Glory, Dominion, Praiſe, Thanks-giving, and Eternal ſongs of deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and Redemptions, over all Heaven and Earth, <hi>Halelujah,</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="advice">
            <p>ALL you Biſhops, Prelates, Preiſts, Epiſcopal men, or any other that are profeſſing God, Chriſt and Scriptures, and are offering Sacrifice in your own wills, and time, and places, out of the fear, and counſel, and wiſdome of God.</p>
            <p>This is the word of the Lord God, you and your Sacrifices are not accepted in his ſight, but are Abomination unto him, even iniquity and Idolatry, and all your prayers, ſingings, preachings, faſtings, feaſtings, and roarings, enters not into the ears of the Lord God of Sabboths, but is a ſmoak in his noſtrils all the day long, and all your Sacrifices, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments (as you call them) are not better in the ſight of the pure living God of Heaven, then if you cut off a Dogs neck, or offered Swines blood, for it is ſo you offer Swines blood, (and not the blood of the Lamb with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot, the acceptable ſeed) and the broth of Abominable things (which the Lord abhors) is in your Veſſels; if you have ears to hear, hear, you offer Swines blood, the life of the Swine (the greedy devourer) that lives in your dwellings, in which the Devils is entered, and you are running violently down the ſteep place, and you will periſh among the waters if you Repent not, and turn ſpeedily, the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>Therefore hear, hear you that are offering Sacrifice, and prayers, (called Common) and are in your will Worſhips, and feigned humility, never commanded of God, &amp; though you make a great noyſe with your Organs, and Sacraments, and Surplices, and Tippits, and Girdles, and tables, and fingings, and pipings, and ringings, and the like, its all but as the hidious howling of a Dog at midnight, whilſt you live in luſts, envy, pride, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43937:8"/> coveteouſneſs,, and unrighteousneſs, and no more accepted of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous holy, juſt God, then <hi>Cains</hi> was (the Vagabond) who ſlew his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being in the ſame nature and ground of malice, and wickedneſs, and God hath ſet a mark upon you, (as upon <hi>Cain</hi>) which ſhall never be blotted out, unleſs you turn, and be converted (from that root) and ſink down in your minds to the righteous ſuffering ſeed in you, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had fellowſhip in theſe things in which you are thus excerciſed, but reproves you in ſecret for ſin, and lets you ſee the evil and vanity of your ways.</p>
            <p>For while you do evil ſin lyeth at your door, and your prayers and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices do not enter into the acceptance of the holy God, for God heareth not ſinners, but if any man be a Worſhiper of God, and doth his will him he heareth, but none worſhips God, but them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth, even in that ſpirit which you dayly greive and provoke with your abominations, and Sacrifices, and Oblations, ſinning, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which he is weary to bear, of which he will ſhortly eaſe himſelf, and of you alſo, if you proceed in theſe things which never came into his mind to commend or require at your hands.</p>
            <p>Therefore hear and conſider, and fear and tremble before the juſt God of power, who is ariſen to plead with you about theſe things, and will reprove you for your words, worſhips, and Sacrifices, feigned imitations, which are without the true knowledge, darkening the Counſel of God in your own ſelves and others, whereby his pure way of life and truth is not heeded, but evil ſpoken of, and his Eternal Counſel (by you) is not underſtood, which is to ſtand ſtill in the Light of Chriſt Jeſus the Saviour, and not will, nor run, but as led and guided by it; which leads out of all unrighteouſneſs, into ſoberneſs, goodneſs, equity, &amp; all truth, &amp; it will let you ſee (if you are quiet in your minds) that the jealous God of holineſs, hath no fellowſhip, nor delight in your ways of ſuperſtition and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but ſecretly ſaith, Returne returne, this is not your reſt for it is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted; but and if you will not hear, and come into the ſtill waters of <hi>Shiloah,</hi> which run ſaftly, but will ſtill ride upon Horſes, even go on in the ſtrength of your wills in your great noyſe of falſe worſhips, ways, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and ungodlineſs, then they that perſue you (even the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God) ſhall be very ſwift againſt you faith the Lord God of Hoſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is your warning, and viſitation as ſhall be witneſſed whether you hear or forbear.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="questions">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:43937:9"/>
            <head>Some occaſional Queries concerning a Vagabond.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. Qu.</hi> VVHether the ground of being a Vagabond, be the want of an outward Inheritance, Habitation, or earthly riches, or certain dwelling place in the Earth (as ſome have ſaid) yea or nay, if yea, then how was <hi>Cain</hi> as a Vagabond, ſeeing he was a Rich man, and had an Inheritance and certain dwelling place in the Earth, who builded a City, and called it after the name of his ſon, <hi>Gen. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. Qu.</hi> And if the want of an outward Inheritance, or certain dwelling place in the Earth be the only ground of being a Vagabond, then whether <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was a Vagabond when he went out of his own Country, not knowing whether he went, (having not ſo much ground as to ſet his foot on,) of whom it is written, he is called the freind of God, <hi>Acts 7. Heb. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For there hath been a great noiſe in the World, amongſt the Rich and great men, and profeſſors thereof, in theſe latter days, ſaying, if you cannot give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your certain dwelling place, habitation, or place of aboad in the earth, we account you as Vagabonds, and wanderers, and Rogues, and you muſt be proſecuted againſt as ſuch, by our Law, Ordinace, or Act of Parliament or the like; which if they have ſuch a Law that doth Iudge &amp; conclude, ſuch to be Vagabonds as have no certain dwelling place in the earth &amp; that this (in their account) is the ground of being a Vagabond, then marke how far this Law will reach.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. Qu.</hi> Whether it will not reach as far in this caſe as did the Scribs and Phariſees, the <hi>Jews</hi> Law, to the ſon of God, who ſaid we have a Law, and by our Law he ought to dye, for ſaid Chriſt, the Foxes have holes, (ſuch as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi>) and the fowles of the Aire have neſts, (of whome the Devil is Ruler) but the ſon of man hath no where to lay his head.</p>
            <p>Now this Law taks hold of him, and of <hi>Abraham</hi> his freind, and of his Apoſtles and Prophets in the days paſt who wandered in Sheep-skins, and Goat-skins, being deſtitute and afflicted, having no certain dwelling place: But if you ſay nay, theſe are no Vagabonds, though Chriſt had not a place to lay his head on, nor <hi>Abraham</hi> a foot of ground, and wandered into a ſtrange Country, not knowing whether he went, and the Apoſtles and Patriarks wandered, and were in Dens and Caves of the Earth, being deſtitute, afflicted, and tormented by the wicked men of the World (who was not worthy of them) having no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43937:9"/> dwelling place, yet theſe were no Vagabonds, but good men, Righteous men, ſincere and holy men of God.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4. Qu.</hi> Then what is the abſolute ground of being a Vagabond, ſeeing theſe men are no Vagabonds, though they have no certaine dwelling place (but wandred up and down) in the earth, and that <hi>Cain</hi> is a Vagabond, though a rich man and builded a Citty.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5. Qu.</hi> Whether the word [Vagabond] doth not ſignifie a ſeperation or wandring from God (who is truth and love) or a being baniſhed from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, by reaſon of envy, murther, and rage, which ſeperates from the pure juſt God.</p>
            <p>For Cain ſaid (when he had been wrath and had ſlain his brother,) now ſhall I bee a Vagabond and a fugitive in the Earth, and from thy preſence ſhall I be hid (mark that) and behold every one that findeth me, will ſ ay me, ſo he fled from the preſence of the Lord, and dwelt in the Land of <hi>Nod,</hi> (on the Eaſt of <hi>Eden,</hi>) where this Murderer built a City (a ſtrong hold) being afraid every one that found him would kill him, mark here the firſt builder in the Earth was a Vagabond, a rich man a perſecutor, and a Murderer about Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, <hi>Gen. 45.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6. Qu.</hi> Now whether envy, wrath, perſecution, murder, cruelty, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and impriſoning about Sacrifice and Worſhip, be not the very ground and cauſe of being a Vagabond, or ſeperated from God and not the want of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dwelling place in the Earth.</p>
            <p>Seeing <hi>Cain</hi> is a Vagabond, though he builded a City, and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Apoſtles and Prophets, and many other holy men of God and Chriſt, are no Vagabonds, though they wandred and had no City, houſe, or dwelling place in the Earth, or ſo much ground as to ſet their foot, or to lay their head on.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7. Qu.</hi> Whether God hath not choſen the poor of this world, rich in faith, and heires of his everlaſting Kingdome, and whether the rich men that did oppreſs them, and draw them before Iudgements ſeats, were not the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and ſuch as tormented and afflicted them, in envy, ambition, and wrath, were not the Vagabonds, ſeeing ſuch things ſeperates from God, and hides his preſence from them.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8. Qu.</hi> Whether <hi>Lazarus</hi> was a Vagabond, who was very poor, and lay begging at the rich mans Gate, where the Dogs came, in more love then their owner) ticking his ſores, or whether this hard hearted Rich man was not the Vagabond, ſeeing he was caſt into Hell torments, where he was ſeperated (with a great Gulf) from the preſence and Glory of Gods love for ever, and <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> the begger carried into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, (the friend of God) by an Angel, being comforted, and the other (who lived in pleaſures unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and deliciouſneſs, every day in his life time) tormented <hi>Luke 16.</hi> He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43937:10"/>
            <p>Now ſeeing <hi>Cain</hi> is a Vagabond, being in the wrath, envy, &amp; tranſgreſſion, (the ground of it;) Let us ſearch the line of true Iudgement yet further, and ſee if we can finde more rich men to be Vagabonds, and Blaſphemers, though they have Citys (like <hi>Cain,</hi>) or habitations in the Earth.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9. Qu.</hi> Whether <hi>Iſhmael</hi> (the wild man the mocke and ſcoffer) was not caſt out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe (the freind of God) into whoſe boſom the poor man <hi>Lazarus</hi> was carried and whether he was not ſeperated by his wildneſs mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and enmity, (whoſe hand was againſt every man, and every mans hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him,) from the preſence of God and was a Vagabond, ſeeing the word Vagabond ſignifies a ſeperation, or being driven from, (or caſt out of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10. Qu.</hi> Whether <hi>Eſau</hi> the cunning Hunter the prophane perſon, was not a Vagabond, ſeeing he ſould his Birth-right for a meſs of Pottage and loſt the bleſſing, and afterwards ſought a place of Repentance, but could not finde it, (but was rejected,) though he ſought it carefully with tears; (conſider this ye prophane and ungodly ones, whoſe pleaſures, and treaſures are in this life) out of whoſe Loyns came the Dukes of <hi>Edom,</hi> and twelve Princes from the Loynes of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> (the wild man the mocker and ſcoffer, who was caſt out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe,) and theſe had Towns and Caſtles (like their brother <hi>Cain</hi>) and great poſſeſſions in the Earth, <hi>Gen. 21.9, 25.16, 36.40. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 12.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11. Qu.</hi> Whether ſuch as are in the envious wrathful, wild, mocking, and ſcoffing nature. <hi>[Now]</hi> and are prophane perſons cunningly hunting <hi>[Now]</hi> and perſecuting and afflicting about Sacrifice <hi>[Now]</hi> and drawing the poor of this world, (wh are choſen rich in faith, and heirs of Gods Kingdome) before the Iudgement ſeats <hi>[Now,]</hi> Whether theſe are not the Blaſphemers, Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, and ſeperated from Gods preſence <hi>[Now]</hi> (in this ſtate) though they may be great and rich in this world (as the Princes of <hi>Iſhmael Cain,</hi> and the Dukes of <hi>Edom,</hi>) ſeeing God hath choſen the poor of this world rich in fai h, and heirs of his Kingdom without end, from which <hi>Cain</hi> was a Vagabond, though he builded a City, and called it after the name of his ſon, <hi>Gen. 4.17.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="warning">
            <p>THerefore hearken all you Kings, Rulers, Governours and people up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, and take heed you do not perſecute and impriſon, or abuſe the ſervants and Children of the moſt high God, (wherever they come in your Dominions or Countrys) under the name of Vagabonds, wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or Idle perſons, or the like, (who come in love to your ſouls;) And be you warned that you hurt not them, who do no evil, I charge you in the name of the dreadful God that made heaven and earth, leaſt you bring Innocent blood upon your own heads, and as you will anſwer it in the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible day at hand, for the Almighty God is no reſpecter of perſons, (who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43937:10"/> is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords;) neither doth poverty or riches in this world, make a Vagabond, or keep from being a Vagabond, for they were no Vagabonds, who had here no continuing City, but ſought one to come, whoſe builder &amp; maker is God, though they wandered about in ſheep skins, &amp; Goat skins, in Dens &amp; Caves of the earth, yet theſe were no Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, but had a habitation in God, of whom they obtained a good report, through faith, and were bleſſed; of whom the world was not worthy.</p>
            <p>And if any of us, who are of the ſame ſeed, and generation, and built upon the ſame foundation Chriſt Jeſus, (the Light that lighteth every man,) who was hated, ſcorned, derided, and drawn from priſon to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I ſay if any of us who declare his Generation now, (by afflictions, perſecutions, cruel mockings impriſonments, and drawing before Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeats) ſhould like <hi>Abraham</hi> in obedience to the voice of the Lord God of our fathers, go out of our own Countrys, not knowing whether we went, even we who are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> (that tremble at his word,) yet we are no Vagabonds, but obedient children and ſervants of the moſt high God of power, and compaſſions, before whom all Nations ſhall bow and tremble; Therefore be awakened all ye Rulers and Inhabitants of the Earth, and conſider theſe things, and be not raſh heady, nor high minded, nor haſty to give heed to falſe reports, or to fulfil the luſts and wills of envious wrathful and ambitious men, or to lay hands ſuddenly, or violently on any, without juſt cauſe, but be meek, patient, and ſober, and ſearch out the truth of cauſes, and controverſies, and conſider the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures before written, for the people of the living God, are at this day ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Pilgrims in the Earth, as all our fathers were; Therefore fear God, and be very careful, (heeding the light, his witneſs in you which lets you ſee between good and evil) for ſome have entertained Angles unawares, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.2.</p>
            <p>Be wiſe thererore now O ye Kings and Rulers, and be inſtructed, and learn Righteouſneſs, ye that be Juddges of the Earth, and ſerve the God with fear and trembling, leaſt his anger be wholly kindled againſt you, and then you periſh from the way of everlaſting peace and happyneſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am a lover of the Holy God and good men of truth, mercy, and Righteouſneſs, and am w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing in the ſpirit of Love and patience for the Reſurrection of the dead, that the Righteous and holy ſeed may ariſe, and come into Rule and Dominon, in and through the whole Creation, called</hi> VVilliam Bayly.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <l>THe decree of God, the firſt Birth is to ſlay,</l>
            <l>That all its fruits and Offspring might decay,</l>
            <l>Which hath ſild the Earth with Pride and Violence</l>
            <l>Even like the Plague, and grevious Peſtilence;</l>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:43937:11"/>
            <l>The zeal of God, againſt it now doth burn,</l>
            <l>Which will conſum't, in <hi>Iacobs</hi> bleſt return;</l>
            <l>For the firſt born of <hi>Egypt,</hi> muſt be brought</l>
            <l>To death, who hath the ſeconds miſcheif ſought,</l>
            <l>Which now muſt rule, the Nations with his Rod,</l>
            <l>Though <hi>Cain</hi> may flee, and build i'th Land of <hi>Nod,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yet there his hand, will finde him out again,</l>
            <l>Then endleſs will be, his puniſhment and pain,</l>
            <l>And all that came from the firſt Birth muſt go</l>
            <l>In't Condemnation, and eternal woe,</l>
            <l>Which caus'd the wrath of God, on earth to come,</l>
            <l>Therefore its great deſtruction, is the Sun</l>
            <l>Of what the Prophets by paſt, have declar'd</l>
            <l>That <hi>Babylon</hi> no longer ſhould be ſpar'd,</l>
            <l>But Vengeance on her head, ſhould poured be,</l>
            <l>That all her Plagues, and nakedneſs may ſee,</l>
            <l>And by her Torments learn, for to amend,</l>
            <l>Leaſt furious Plagues, again on them he ſend;</l>
            <l>For with his ſword hee'l cut down <hi>Ceadars</hi> tall,</l>
            <l>And with great noyſe, Now <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt fall,</l>
            <l>And all her Merchants, they ſhall weep and wail,</l>
            <l>For God will neither leave her, head nor tail,</l>
            <l>And hee'l not ſpare his Arrows for to ſpend</l>
            <l>Till of her ſeed h'hath made a final end;</l>
            <l>All fleſh ſhall fail, all knees ſhall feeble be</l>
            <l>The Joynts and Loyns of men, now loos'd you'l ſee,</l>
            <l>The Earth ſhall reel, the Mountains they ſhall quake,</l>
            <l>Becauſe God pleads with them for his Seeds ſake,</l>
            <l>Theſe things are neer, and haſten they do now</l>
            <l>The time is come, that Nations all muſt bow</l>
            <l>To him that's born, who muſt the Scepter ſway,</l>
            <l>And bring to duſt, what ſtands againſt his way</l>
            <l>His <hi>Name</hi> is <hi>Light</hi> his burthen is ſo to,</l>
            <l>Eaſy his Yoak, to thoſe who life for-goe,</l>
            <l>And in his Name ſake, and in his will can reſt,</l>
            <l>Theſe are the Souls that are for ever bleſt</l>
            <l>But as for them that will not he ſhould Reign</l>
            <l>The time draws neer, in which they muſt be ſlain. <hi>Amen</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ha le lu jah.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. B</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Babylon <hi>the Great is fallen is fallen, and become the habitation of Devils,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Revel. 18.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>THE END</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43937:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
